Register of the David Benjamin Bolen Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Albums,., 1946-2001 (Box 1)
  - No. 51-A,., 1978-1979 (Box 21)
    - Part one (Folder 21: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 21: 2)
  - No. 51-B,., 1978
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, especially with regard to commercial relations between the United States and the GDR
    - Part one (Folder 21: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 21: 4)
  - No. 52,., 1978-1980 (Folder 21: 5)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, with an emphasis on negotiations conducted with the GDR over the issues of the repatriation of cultural property and Jewish material claims made against the GDR for losses suffered under the Nazis
  - No. 53,., 1979-1980 (Box-folder 22: 1)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic. Includes official correspondence pertaining to the defection to West Germany in 1979 of an East German driver working for the American embassy in East Berlin
  - No. 54,., 1978-1979 (Folder 22: 2)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic. Includes official correspondence pertaining to East German coverage of neo-Nazi activities in West Germany, and to American reaction to East German positions taken during the World Conference to Combat Racism and Racial Discrimination, Geneva, 1978. Also contains correspondence relating to the American investigation of war crimes committed during the Nazi era, and to the request by the United States of judicial assistance from the GDR in this matter
  - No. 55,., 1978-1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to the hijacking of a Polish airliner by an East German citizen, 1978 August 30, and his subsequent trial by American authorities in West Berlin
    - Part one (Folder 22: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 22: 4)
  - No. 56,., 1980
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to the Iranian hostage crisis and its repercussions in terms of East-West relations
    - Part one (Folder 22: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 22: 6)
  - No. 57,., 1979 (Box 23)
    - Part one (Folder 23: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 23: 2)
  - No. 58,., 1980
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan and its effects on US-GDR relations
    - Part one (Folder 23: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 23: 4)
  - No. 59,., 1978-1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to the 18th anniversary of the erection of the Berlin Wall and other issues related to the divided status of Berlin
    - Part one (Folder 23: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 23: 6)
  - No. 60,., 1979-1980 (Box 24)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to economic and political developments within the GDR
    - Part one. (Folder 24: 1)
      Includes assessments by Bolen and others of the degree of political liberalization in the GDR, and of the cases of the East German dissidents, Rudolf Bahro and Stefan Heym
    - Part two (Folder 24: 2)
  - No. 61,., 1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to East-West tensions arising over the disputed status of Berlin
    - Part one (Folder 24: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 24: 4)
  - No. 62,., 1978-1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to relations between East and West Germany
    - Part one (Folder 24: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 24: 6)
  - No. 63,., 1977-1979 (Box 25)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to economic developments in the GDR and elsewhere in Eastern Europe
    - Part one (Folder 25: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 25: 2)
  - No. 64,., 1977-1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to the promotion of trade between the United States and the GDR
    - Part one. (Folder 25: 3)
      Includes some interpolated memoranda from Bolen's period of employment with the Du Pont Company, 1985
    - Part two (Folder 25: 4)
  - No. 65,., 1978-1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to an international postal agreement concluded by the United States and the GDR
    - Part one (Folder 25: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 25: 6)
  - No. 66,., 1979 (Box 26)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to access to Berlin under the terms of international agreements, and to the SALT II negotiations conducted by the United States and the Soviet Union
    - Part one (Folder 26: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 26: 2)
  - No. 67,., 1978-1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to disputes between the United States and the GDR over the divided status of Berlin
    - Part one (Folder 26: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 26: 4)
  - No. 68,., 1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to American access to East Berlin under the terms of an existing international agreement
    - Part one (Folder 26: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 26: 6)
  - No. 69,., 1979 (Box 27)
    - Part one (Folder 27: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 27: 2)
  - No. 70,., 1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to reported violations of the quadripartite agreement on the status of Berlin
    - Part one (Folder 27: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 27: 4)
  - No. 71,., 1979
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to issues of arms control and disarmament
    - Part one (Folder 27: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 27: 6)
  - No. 72,., 1979 (Box 28)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of official correspondence pertaining to the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan, and its consequences in terms of relations between the United States and the GDR
    - Part one (Folder 28: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 28: 2)
  - No. 73,., 1977-1978
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of typescripts of speeches and other prepared remarks delivered by Bolen in his diplomatic career
    - Part one. (Folder 28: 3)
      Includes typescript of a speech by Bolen on African affairs, Colorado University Alumni Symposium, Boulder, Colorado, 1977 April 27-28
    - Part two. (Folder 28: 4)
      Includes typescript of a speech by Bolen on East German affairs, Rotary Club, Lexington, Kentucky, 1978 February 16
  - No. 74,., 1976-1977
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to Botswana, Lesotho, and Swaziland, and as Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for African Affairs
    - Part one (Folder 28: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 28: 6)
  - No. 75,., 1981-1984
    Materials relating to Bolen's work for E. I. du Pont de Nemours and Co., consisting primarily of correspondence and reports pertaining to South Africa, domestic and foreign opposition to its apartheid system, and the implementation of the Sullivan principles by companies doing business in that country
    - Part one (Folder 29: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 29: 2)
    - Part three (Folder 29: 3)
  - No. 76,., 1985
    - Part one (Folder 29: 4)
    - Part two (Folder 29: 5)
  - No. 77,., 1985 (Box 30)
    - Part one (Folder 30: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 30: 2)
  - No. 78,., 1985-1986
    - Part one (Folder 30: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 30: 4)
  - No. 79,., 1985
    - Part one (Folder 30: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 30: 6)
  - No. 80,., 1985-1986 (Box 31)
    - Part one (Folder 31: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 31: 2)
  - No. 81,., 1986
    - Part one (Folder 31: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 31: 4)
  - No. 82,., 1986
    - Part one (Folder 31: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 31: 6)
  - No. 83,., 1987-1990 (Box 32)
    - Part one. (Folder 32: 1)
      Includes printed copy of a speech by Bolen, "International Business against Apartheid: Toward Optimum Resource Deployment," International Conference on South Africa in Transition: The Process and Prospects of Creating a Nonracial, Democratic Nation of South Africa, Baruch College Center for Management, New York, 1987 September 29-October 2
    - Part two (Folder 32: 2)
  - No. 84,., 1986
    - Part one. (Folder 32: 3)
      Includes printed copy of remarks by Secretary of State George P. Shultz, Conference on South Africa for American Religious Leaders, Washington, D.C., 1986 June 2
    - Part two (Folder 32: 4)
  - No. 85,., 1989-1990
    Materials relating to Bolen's work for E. I. du Pont de Nemours and Co., consisting primarily of correspondence and reports pertaining to South Africa, domestic and foreign opposition to its apartheid system, and the application of the Sullivan principles to companies doing business in that country
    - Part one (Folder 32: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 32: 6)
  - No. 86,., 1982-1990 (Box 33)
    - Part one (Folder 33: 1)
    - Part two. (Folder 33: 2)
      Includes some correspondence relating to the observance of the MacBride principles by companies doing business in Northern Ireland, including Du Pont
  - No. 87,., 1990-1992
    - Part one (Folder 33: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 33: 4)
  - No. 88,., 1984-1990
    - Part one (Folder 33: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 33: 6)
  - No. 89,., 1985-1986 (Box 34)
    - Part one (Folder 34: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 34: 2)
  - No. 90,., 1980-1985
    Materials relating to Bolen's work for E. I. du Pont de Nemours and Co., consisting primarily of speeches and reports by Bolen on the subjects of international business, African affairs, and East-West relations
    - Part one. (Folder 34: 3)
      Includes typescript of a speech by Bolen, "Perceptions of the United States as Observed in Warsaw Pact and African Countries," World Affairs Council, Wilmington, Delaware, 1981 June 29
    - Part two. (Folder 34: 4)
      Includes printed copy of a speech by Bolen, "Change, Challenge and Opportunity in the World of Work," National Alliance of Business 14th Annual College/Industry Relations Conference, Norfolk, Virginia, 1982 January 25
  - No. 91,., 1993
    Correspondence and clippings relating to political developments in South Africa and Germany, with some clippings pertaining to the Mid-East conflict and to American foreign policy in general
    - Part one (Folder 34: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 34: 6)
  - No. 92,., 1993 (Box 35)
    Materials relating to Bolen's work for E. I. du Pont de Nemours and Co., consisting primarily of correspondence and reports pertaining to South Africa, and lifting of economic sanctions against that country in the wake of the dismantling of its apartheid system
    - Part one. (Folder 35: 1)
      Includes some clippings relating to economic and political conditions in Germany following reunification
    - Part two (Folder 35: 2)
  - No. 94,., 1994
    Clippings relating to political developments in South Africa and Germany, and to East-West relations in general
    - Part one (Folder 35: 3)
    - Part two (Folder 35: 4)
  - No. 95,., 1990
    Materials relating to Bolen's work for E. I. du Pont de Nemours and Co., consisting primarily of correspondence and reports pertaining to South Africa, the implementation of the Sullivan principles by Du Pont, and visits to the United States by Nelson Mandela and F. W. de Klerk
    - Part one (Folder 35: 5)
    - Part two (Folder 35: 6)
  - No. 96,., 1991 (Box 36)
    Materials relating to Bolen's work for E. I. du Pont de Nemours and Co., and consisting primarily of clippings and correspondence pertaining to South Africa and American policy toward that country. Includes some clippings and correspondence regarding economic conditions in Germany following reunification
    - Part one (Folder 36: 1)
    - Part two (Folder 36: 2)
  - No. 97,., 1960-1963
    Materials relating to Bolen's academic studies and diplomatic career, consisting of research papers and public speeches written by Bolen, most of which concern economic conditions in Africa
    - Part one. (Folder 36: 3)
      Includes typescript of research paper, "Psycho-Sociological Analysis of the Race Problem and Its Impact on U.S. Foreign Relations in Sub-Sahara Africa," U.S. Department of State, Foreign Service Institute, 1960 September 22
    - Part two. (Folder 36: 4)
      Includes typescript of speech, "Problems and Prospects for Economic Development in Africa," Fourth Annual Institute on African Life and History, Hampton Institute, Hampton, Virginia, 1963 July 12
  - Unnumbered album,., 1985
    Materials relating to Bolen's participation in the activities of the World Affairs Council of Wilmington, Delaware, and to his work for E. I. du Pont de Nemours and Co., consisting primarily of correspondence and reports on American foreign policy issues
    - Part one. (Folder 36: 5)
      Includes correspondence relating to a visit to Wilmington by the Chinese ambassador to the United States, Zhang Wenjin
    - Part two. (Folder 36: 6)
      Includes correspondence relating to a visit to Wilmington by the former British prime minister, Edward Heath
  - No. 98,., 1961-1977 (Box 37)
    Materials relating to Bolen's academic studies and diplomatic career, consisting of articles, research papers, and public speeches written by Bolen, most of which concern economic conditions in Africa
    - Part one. (Folder 37: 1)
      Includes printed copy of article, "Economic Development in Africa," Foreign Service Journal, 1964 May
    - Part one. (Folder 37: 2)
      Includes typescript of research paper, "Genesis of Socio-Political Disequilibria in Africa and Its Implication for U.S. Policy," National War College, Washington, D.C., 1967 May 19
  - No. 99-A,., 1977-1996
    Materials relating to Bolen's diplomatic and business careers, consisting of correspondence and public speeches written by Bolen, most of which pertain to American foreign policy and business practices vis-à-vis Germany and Africa
    - Part one. (Folder 37: 3)
      Includes printed copy of speech, "International Business in a Multi-Cultural World," Conference on Cross-Cultural Awareness and the Business Community, Goldey Beacom College, Wilmington, Delaware, 1983 October 22
    - Part two. (Folder 37: 4)
      Includes typescript of speech, "German Unification: Defense or Détente," German Unification Day, American/German Chamber of Commerce, Denver, Colorado, 1996 October 3
  - No. 99-B,., 1971-1997
    Materials relating to Bolen's diplomatic and business career, consisting of correspondence and public speeches written by Bolen, most of which pertain to issues of German reunification and economic conditions in Africa
    - Part one. (Folder 37: 5)
      Includes typescript of speech, "U.S. Interests and Objectives in Western Europe," Bates College, Luxembourg, 1971 April 21
    - Part two. (Folder 37: 6)
      Includes typescript of speech, "German Unification and the Future of Europe," Colorado Consular Corps luncheon, Denver, Colorado, 1997 February 25
  - No. 100,., 1977-1998 (Box 38)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting primarily of official correspondence and reports on bilateral relations between the United States and East Germany
    - Part one. (Folder 38: 1)
      Includes transcript of a speech by President Bill Clinton commemorating the 50th anniversary of the Berlin Airlift, Schauspielhaus, Berlin, 1998 May 13
    - Part two. (Folder 38: 2)
      Includes transcript of a speech by Chancellor Helmut Kohl commemorating the 50th anniversary of the Berlin Airlift, Tempelhof Airport, Berlin, 1998 May 14
  - No. 101,., 1977-1999
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting primarily of clippings and official correspondence pertaining to bilateral relations between the United States and East Germany, the divided status of Berlin, and East-West relations in general
    - Part one. (Folder 38: 3)
      Including clippings and correspondence regarding the flight of East German citizens to West Germany
    - Part two (Folder 38: 4)
  - No. 102,., 1977-1978
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting primarily of photographs and official correspondence pertaining to American exhibits at trade fairs in Leipzig in 1977 and 1978
    - Part one. (Folder 38: 5)
      Includes photographs of Ambassador Bolen greeting Erich Honecker, Chairman of the Council of State of the GDR, at the Leipzig Fall Fair, 1977
    - Part two. (Folder 38: 6)
      Includes photographs of Ambassador Bolen greeting Erich Honecker, Chairman of the Council of State of the GDR, at the Leipzig Fall Fair, 1978
  - No. 103,., 1978-1996
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, and to his work concerning East Germany for E. I. du Pont de Nemours and Co. Consists of clippings, official correspondence, and reports, largely pertaining to economic and political developments in East Germany
    - Part one. (Folder 39: 1)
      Includes clippings and correspondence relating to the Berlin Wall, and to the official view of the GDR government on this issue
    - Part two. (Folder 39: 2)
      Contains typescript of a speech by Hermann Axen, Chairman of the Foreign Affairs Committee of the People's Chamber of the German Democratic Republic, Johns Hopkins University, Washington, D.C., 1988 May 5
  - No. 104,., 1977-1998 (Folder 39: 3)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting primarily of official correspondence pertaining to cultural exchanges between the United States and the GDR, and to the signing of a consular convention between these two countries. Includes typescript of remarks given by Bolen concerning the sending to Germany of a sculpture about the dismantling of the Berlin Wall, Denver, Colorado, 1998 June 6
  - No. 105,., 1985-1996 (Folder 39: 4)
    Materials relating to Bolen's work for E. I. du Pont de Nemours and Co., consisting primarily of correspondence and reports pertaining to South Africa, its apartheid system, and the implementation of the Sullivan principles by companies doing business in that country. Includes typescript of statement by Rev. Leon Sullivan urging complete withdrawal of foreign companies from South Africa, 1987 June 3
  - No. 106,., 1977-1992
    Materials relating to Bolen's work for E. I. du Pont de Nemours and Co., consisting primarily of correspondence and reports pertaining to South Africa, its apartheid system, and the implementation of the Sullivan principles by companies doing business in that country
    - Part one. (Folder 39: 5)
      Includes typescript of speech by Bolen, "North-South Dialogue: Reality of Interdependence," University of Iowa, 1977 June 10
    - Part two. (Folder 39: 6)
      Includes one memorandum concerning Du Pont's operations in Northern Ireland, 1990 April 10
  - No. 107-A,., 1987 (Box 40)
    - Part one (Folder 40: 1)
    - Part two. (Folder 40: 2)
      Includes typescript of a speech by Secretary of State George P. Shultz, "The Democratic Future of South Africa," Business Council for International Understanding, New York, New York, 1987 September 29
  - No. 107-B,., 1977-1980 (Folder 40: 3)
    Materials relating to Bolen's duties as Ambassador to the German Democratic Republic, consisting largely of photographs and post cards. Includes photographs of Ambassador Bolen, Betty Bolen, and Warren Christopher
  - No. 108,., 1955-1980
    Materials relating to Bolen's diplomatic and business career, consisting primarily of official correspondence and reports pertaining to postings in Pakistan, Africa, Yugoslavia, and the German Democratic Republic
    - Part one (Folder 40: 4)
    - Part two. (Folder 40: 5)
      Includes a memorandum written by G. Mennen Williams to President John F. Kennedy on the subject of civil rights, 1963 June 14
  - No. 109,., 1947-2001 (Folder 40: 6)
    Materials relating to Bolen's induction into the University of Colorado's Hall of Fame, 2000 August 10, and to his being recognized as a distinguished alumnus during the 125th anniversary celebration of the University of Colorado, 2001 April 20. Consists of clippings, correspondence, diplomas, and a list of awards, as arranged by Ambassador Bolen in an overview of his athletic, diplomatic, and business careers
  - Unnumbered,., 1947-2001 (Folder 40: 7)
    Materials relating to Bolen's receiving of the Distinguished Business Service Award by the University of Colorado, 1997, and to his being recognized as a distinguished alumnus during the 125th anniversary celebration of the University of Colorado, 2001 April 20. Consists of clippings, correspondence, diplomas, and list of awards, as arranged by Ambassador Bolen in an overview of his athletic, diplomatic, and business careers
  - Unnumbered,., 1947-2001 (Folder 40: 8)
    Materials relating to Bolen's being recognized as a distinguished alumnus during the 125th anniversary celebration of the University of Colorado, 2001 April 20. Consists of clippings, correspondence, curriculum vitae, diplomas, and list of awards, as arranged by Ambassador Bolen in an overview of his athletic, diplomatic, and business careers
  - Speeches, (unnumbered)., 1963-1997 (Box 41)
    Public addresses and remarks delivered by Ambassador Bolen on subjects of American foreign policy and international business affairs, especially in relation to the German Democratic Republic and South Africa
    - "Problems and Prospects for Economic Development in Africa," Fourth Annual Institute on African Life and History, Hampton Institute, Hampton, Virginia,., 1963 July 12 (Folder 41: 1)
      Typescript
    - "U.S. Interests and Objectives in Western Europe," Bates College, Luxembourg,., 1971 April 21 (Folder 41: 2)
    - "United States Relations with Africa South of the Sahara," Colorado Association for International Education Symposium on Africa South of the Sahara, Air Force Academy, Colorado Springs, Colorado,., 1976 November 12 (Folder 41: 3)
    - "The Third World - New Dimensions," Colorado University Alumni Symposium, Boulder, Colorado,., 1977 April 27-28 (Folder 41: 4)
    - Address on African affairs, Fourth Annual Meeting of the African Development Fund, Port Louis, Mauritius,., 1977 May (Folder 41: 5)
    - "North-South Dialogue: Reality of Interdependence," University of Iowa,., 1977 June 10 (Folder 41: 6)
    - "U.S.-GDR Relations in a Rapidly Changing World," University of Kentucky, Lexington, Kentucky,., 1978 February 16 (Folder 41: 7)
    - "U.S.-GDR Relations," Rotary Club, Lexington, Kentucky,"., 1978 February 16 (Folder 41: 8)